<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvatch for a wise mans observation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.4[231]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885053</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06485)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:2[232])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvatch for a wise mans observation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Thackeray, at the sign of the Angel in Ducklane:,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "One God there is, of wisdom, glory, might ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:182900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>A VVATCH For a Wiſe Mans OBSERVATION.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the moving parts of a clock</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>ONe <hi>God</hi> there is, of Wiſdom, Glory, Might,</l>
                  <l>One <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi> there is, to guide our Souls aright,</l>
                  <l>One truth there is, that Errours doth deſcry,</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> for to know all Chriſtian by.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Two <hi>Teſtaments</hi> there are, the Old and New,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> thou maid view,</l>
                  <l>The one for <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Deeds</hi> doth Precepts give,</l>
                  <l>The other ſaies, the <hi>Juſt</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> ſhall live.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Three <hi>Perſons</hi> in the Glorious <hi>Trinity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make one True <hi>God</hi> in perfect <hi>Unity;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> theſe Three,</l>
                  <l>For ever Equal, and <hi>Eternal</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Four Holy, Bleſſed <hi>Sanctified</hi> Men,</l>
                  <l>(For Comfort of all Chriſtians) that did Pen</l>
                  <l>Our Saviours <hi>Birth Life, Death,</hi> and his <hi>Aſcending,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereof our <hi>Faith</hi> muſt have true comprehending.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>Five <hi>Senſes</hi> do in every Man maintain,</l>
                  <l>A Governing of Power, Rule, and Raign,</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Hearing, Seeing, Taſting, Feeling, Smelling,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which all at <hi>Death</hi> will leave thee, &amp; their dwelling.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Days</hi> thou haſt to Labour in,</l>
                  <l>(So <hi>Merciful</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y God hath been)</l>
                  <l>Of Seaven, to himſelf he takes but one,</l>
                  <l>Oh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ob him not of that, to leave him none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>Seven <hi>Liberal Arts,</hi> by a <hi>Divine</hi> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t,</l>
                  <l>Vnto Man's Vnderſtanding Soul is tinkt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rhetorich, Grammer, Muſick, Geometry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arithmetick, Logick, and Aſtronomy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>Eight Perſons in the <hi>Ark</hi> of Righteous <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were ſaved, when for Sin God did deſtroy</l>
                  <l>The ſoul deſired <hi>World;</hi> all creatures drown'd,</l>
                  <l>Which in that Ship of ſafety was not found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>Nine <hi>Muſes</hi> like unto the Heavens nine <hi>Sphears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Sacred Tunes</hi> intice inclining <hi>Ears:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To elevate each ſad Melancholly mind,</l>
                  <l>And chear the heart that's dolefully inclin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>Ten <hi>Precepts</hi> God hath in his Law declar'd,</l>
                  <l>Man breaks them all: and ſo unleſs God ſpar'd,</l>
                  <l>And in his <hi>Mercy</hi> did our <hi>Sin remit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our juſt reward were in th' <hi>Infernal</hi> Pit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <l>Eleven <hi>Diſciples</hi> did with <hi>Jeſus</hi> pray,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Judas</hi> did the Son of God betray:</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Covetouſneſs:</hi> for greedy gain he fell,</l>
                  <l>To be <hi>Perditions</hi> Child, condemn'd in Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <l>Twelve <hi>Tribes</hi> there were amongſt our <hi>Fathers</hi> old,</l>
                  <l>Twelve <hi>Articles</hi> our <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> doth hold:</l>
                  <l>Twelve <hi>Gates</hi> in New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> there be,</l>
                  <l>Vnto which <hi>City, Chriſt</hi> bring thee and me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Where is <hi>Alexander?</hi> Where is <hi>Plato?</hi> Where is <hi>Croeſus?</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Alexander<hi>'s Victories,</hi> Plato<hi>'s Wiſdoms,</hi> Creſus <hi>Wealth and Luſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is all Forgot, Conſum'd, and come to Duſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Emperour, King, Nobel, Begger, All</l>
                     <l>Muſt yield to Death, and come when he doth call.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>Time brings to Death, the King, and the Beggar.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <head>Mortuus Eſt.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> Earth of Earth, obſerve this well,</l>
                  <l>When Earth in Earth ſhall come to dwell;</l>
                  <l>Where Earth with Earth ſhall cloſe remain,</l>
                  <l>Till Earth from Earth do riſe again:</l>
                  <l>And Earth before his Iudge do come,</l>
                  <l>For to receive a final doom:</l>
                  <l>If Earth on Earth hath lived ſo,</l>
                  <l>That Earth no fruits of Faith can ſhow</l>
                  <l>Then what reward ſhall Earth expect,</l>
                  <l>That did on Earth his God neglect?</l>
                  <l>O ſerve the Lord with might and power,</l>
                  <l>For here thou haſt no certain hour:</l>
                  <l>Remember Man, when thou cam'ſt here,</l>
                  <l>How Naked, Poor, thou did'ſt appear;</l>
                  <l>And how again (what e're thou have,)</l>
                  <l>Thou naked muſt return to Grave.</l>
                  <l>Thy Wooden Cheſt (a narrow place)</l>
                  <l>A Coffin-lid cloſe up thy face:</l>
                  <l>Thy Soul (if ſaved) to Heaven eyes,</l>
                  <l>Thy body here a rotting lies:</l>
                  <l>Forſaken of thy Friends and Kin,</l>
                  <l>As thou on Earth hadſt never been:</l>
                  <l>When they have brought thee to the Grave,</l>
                  <l>And yeilded Earth what Earth doth crave;</l>
                  <l>They back return from whence they came,</l>
                  <l>Till others do the very ſame,</l>
                  <l>In following them as they did thee,</l>
                  <l>This courſe with all the World will be.</l>
                  <l>And here's thy Portion and thy Lot,</l>
                  <l>With men thou ſhalt be ſoon forget;</l>
                  <l>And ſo into Oblivion paſs,</l>
                  <l>Who! ſuch a Man ſometimes he was:</l>
                  <l>But neither Beauty, Riches, Strength,</l>
                  <l>Could give his Life a Minutes length.</l>
                  <l>Therefore, O Man! think on thy State,</l>
                  <l>Before thy life be out of date;</l>
                  <l>Vnto thy God for Mercy pray,</l>
                  <l>That at thy laſt and Dying-Day,</l>
                  <l>The Glorious Angels may thee bring,</l>
                  <l>Where Bleſſed Saints for ever ſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Licenſed, and Entred according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Thackeray,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ducklane:</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
